WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Subtitles by MemoryOnSmells
http://UKsubtitles.ru.
Are you taking it out? Oh...
Look at this. A man in misery.
Who's in misery?
The King, according to Robert.
Why? He has to deal with a Labour
government. Why do you think?
He doesn't look miserable to me.
He just looks like himself.
What is your objection to Mr MacDonald? That
the Prime Minister is the son of a crofter?
I couldn't care less if he was
the son of Fu Manchu.
What worries me is that our
government is committed
to the destruction of people like us
and everything we stand for.
Well, let's wait and see what
happens before we panic.
Where's Edith? She had some old lady
to see in the village.
What about you? Is everything
settled at the school? What's this?
They swore in Mr Adams' replacement on
the school board. It all went off smoothly.
I thought they might have asked me.
I feel guilty about the school.
I ought to support it more.
Well, I'm giving away the prizes
this year. Come with me.
Barrow, can we clear the tea?
Lady Edith's missed it, and Nanny
will be down shortly.
I'd better run.
Oh, stay and see them.
Just as soon as they're able to
answer back.
Sybbie CAN answer back.
True. Why does she call me Donk?
That game you played - pinning the
tail on the donkey.
Can't I be Grandpapa or something
dignified?
I'm afraid it's Donk for the moment.
I don't want George to catch it.
Here they are.
Here's your grandfather now.
Bye-bye, darlings. Goodbye, Donk.
George, come and sit here, darling.
Put it there and I'll see to it.
Oh, don't be like that.
Ena can manage.
Why should she, any more than me?
We've no proper kitchen maid now, so
we must all muck in.
What's the matter? Daisy's grumbling
because they didn't replace Ivy.
At Skelton Park, they're down to a
butler, a cook, two maids and a
cleaning woman, and that's it.
How on earth does it work?
I couldn't tell you.
Why have the people left?
They prefer to be in factories or
shops. They like the hours better.
Oh... I'll forget my head next.
I came in to remind you it's their
34th wedding anniversary on Saturday week,
so, if you want to do a cake, this
is an advance warning.
I suppose there'll be a dinner of
some sort. Oh, I don't know.
34 years! If I were to marry this
year, what would life be like in 1958?
I doubt I'll be troubled by it.
Do you think we'll leave service?
Well, you'll be fine. You've got Mr
Mason's farm to go to. What about me?
But could I? What do I know about farming
or ordering supplies or doing accounts?
Suppose I can't tackle a new life.
If it's all right with you, I've to
tackle tonight's dinner.
Now, start the salmon pates,
while I do a lemon mayonnaise.
We had good news today. Tim was asked
to be chief of the estate firemen.
Oh, how nice. Many congratulations.
Can I give you some more tea?
No, thank you.
How about you, Marigold? Are you
quite finished?
I just love to see her gurgling
away, so peaceful and happy.
We've almost forgotten she's not one
of our own, haven't we, Tim?
She's just lovely. How pretty your
hair is, darling.
I do wonder where she got her
colouring, but I never knew her parents.
No?
No.
Her mother was an old friend of
Tim's, but I never met either of them.
Oh, is that the time? We mustn't
hold you up.
Good girl.
I should probably go.
Have you got your teddy?
Say goodbye.
Goodbye.
Thank you for... Thank you.
She's got a soft spot for you.
Don't be daft.
I do love this evening light.
Oh, I must tell Lord Merton.
Tease me if you will, but I don't
want to be pursued by him or Lord anyone.
Well, that's a pity - he's asked me
to help him in his courtship.
What?
He doesn't want to pester you,
so he's asked if I could give another
luncheon party.
Oh, dear.
Oh, why the lamentation?
You don't have to see him.
Well, you make it sound so easy.
There's nothing simpler than avoiding
people you don't like.
Avoiding one's friends - that's the
real test.
But I do like him.
I think he's very nice.
It's just, he wants something from
me that I cannot give.
He just wants what all men want.
Oh, don't be ridiculous!
I was referring to companionship.
As I hope you were.
Oh, I didn't mean to disturb you.
I'm sorry. It's a letter from Lady
Anstruther again.
Blimey. She doesn't give up easily.
Well, you know me.
'Irresistible' is my middle name.
Well, was she like this when you
were working for her? Not as bad.
She had to be more discreet with the
other servants.
Hadn't you better go up to London
and put her out of her misery?
Oh, don't tempt me...
because I know this: If I weaken,
I'll pay for it.
This sounds very like the kind of
boys' talk I do not allow.
If you can both tear yourselves away
from your smutty deliberations,
I need you both upstairs.
Where is she?
I hope I'm not late.
No, Carson hasn't come in yet.
That reminds me.
We're to receive a village delegation
tomorrow. I ran into the Postmistress.
She asked if they might pay us a
visit.
Mrs Wigan?
What was it that reminded you?
She asked for Carson to be present.
Why? What's it about?
They want to erect some kind of
memorial to the war. What?
Well, not to the war, but to the men,
the local men, who died in it.
They'll be all over the country.
I suppose they want me as chairman.
Who was it?
Tony Gillingham.
He had some business up here, and
you told him he could stay.
When does he want to come?
That's the problem. The 16th.
And...?
It's our anniversary.
Oh, that doesn't matter.
Ring him and say yes.
We don't have to.
No. I'd like to see him.
Right. That's dinner, everyone.
You don't mind Tony coming, do you?
Not if it's what you want.
I'll tell you what I want.
I want to inspire Tony Gillingham
with thoughts of marriage.
So, does that mean Lord Gillingham
wins and Mr Blake can go whistle?
I'm glad for them. Viscountess
Gillingham - it sounds quite smart.
I think they'll be happy, and it'll
be good for Master George.
It's a big thing, to take on the
task of raising another man's son.
There's nothing to worry about
there. His Lordship's a kind man.
I wish you'd tell me what you know
about those two.
I don't know anything.
What you suspect, then. And don't
deny it, because I've seen you.
You can't stop looking at them when
you think no-one's looking.
Can I join in?
Do you have to?
How was it in York? Did you find
what you were looking for?
I did. Took a bit of a search,
but I think I'm suited.
What's that, then?
Oh, just something.
A group's arriving from the village
tomorrow morning.
Can you get one of the footmen to
bring coffee and something to eat at 11?
Well, find me when you want it.
I can't. I'm in the meeting myself.
That's why I'm telling you now.
What's it for? I don't know, but His
Lordship asked me to be there.
Well, I think it's fantastic.
When did we last have a Prime Minister
who understood the working class? Never.
It's a qualification that is
meaningless in terms of government.
I'm not sure I can agree with you
there. I think it's important.
Me too. Mr MacDonald will have real
experience of a hard life.
He knows what most people go
through.
Up the workers.
So, James is a revolutionary now!
He's not a revolutionary. He believes in justice
for the majority. What's wrong with that?
Nothing, but I suppose he can fight
his own battles.
We'll have no fighting here,
thank you very much.
You wouldn't mind heading
the war-memorial appeal, would you?
I feel a bit embarrassed. I wasn't wounded.
I wasn't even allowed to fight.
They should ask a man like General
McKee or Johnnie Raymond. Someone who
did their bit.
You're their traditional leader and
they like you to pray with them, in
mourning and in gratitude.
But I should be praying in the back
row, not the front. That's all.
Please don't think us too forward.
You have no need to worry.
I'm happy to play my part.
But we don't know yet where we want
the memorial to be, m'lord. So...?
Well, if you're to give us a piece of land, you'd
better know where it is before you agree.
I'm sure I will agree, but is that
why you're here?
To ask for a piece of land as the
site for this thing?
That's why we're here to see you,
m'lord.
But we'd also like to offer the
position of Chairman of our Committee -
I'll take over now.
You were saying...?
We'd like Mr Carson to be Chairman
of our Committee.
But surely, His Lordship...?
No, Carson.
They don't want me - they want you.
I wouldn't put it like that, m'lord,
but Mr Carson knew more of the young
men that died than you did.
Yes, I suppose you're right.
Well, he knew them better.
That's it. And he's a considerable
figure in the village.
Tea, please.
Carson? What do you say?
I am honoured by the invitation,
but I shall have to think about it.
Of course you will.
But please don't take too long.
Can you put my milk in first,
if that's for me?
Did that come in the second post?
It did.
From Lady Anstruther.
Not again? What's stoked her up?
My fault. I shouldn't have sent her
the Valentine.
Yes, but that was -
And I sent her another this year.
How did she know they were from you?
Because I bloody signed them. Oh!
I don't know what I was thinking.
It was supposed to be a joke.
But, well, now it's got out of hand.
Don't worry.
One day I'll be a good boy and
settle down. We all settle down one day.
We don't all have the option.
Heavens! I wasn't expecting you.
I've been to see Smithers at Oak
Field Farm. I just thought I'd look
in on my way home.
I'm glad you did.
I had a delegation from the village,
about the new war memorial
they're putting up.
Oh, they want you to head it?
No.
They've invited Carson to be the
Chairman.
Well, why not you?
The village wanted Carson.
Your father always told the village
what they wanted.
Hmm.
Is it true old Dicky Merton
is paying court to Isobel?
Isn't it absurd?
Oh, it might be rather fun for her to reinvent
herself as a great lady of the county
and put us all in our proper place.
Yes, I suppose it would be fun.
But you don't think she's keen?
Oh, no, far from it. She never tires
of telling me.
Daisy, this came for you in the
post.
Thank you, Mr Carson.
Oh, what is it?
Something I ordered.
May we know what, O Queen?
Something I need.
Why must it be a secret?
Well, it would be a bit sad if she
had no secrets at her age.
Have you made your decision about
the memorial?
Oh, not yet.
I'm not comfortable being placed
ahead of His Lordship.
You should have seen his face,
Mrs Hughes. He felt very let down.
It's the Committee's choice,
and they've chosen you.
And the country's chosen a Labour government,
so people don't always get it right.
What are you afraid of?
I feel a shaking of the ground
I stand on.
That everything I believe in will be
tested and held up for ridicule
over the next few years.
Mr Carson, they've been testing the
system since the Romans left.
Oh, I suppose that's true.
The nature of life is not permanence
but flux.
Just so...
even if it does sound faintly
disgusting.
There you are, m'lady.
Madge said you were going out.
We were giving a turn-out to the
blue room,
and this had been put on the shelf
with the other books.
What is it? A German primer, but the
point is, it's not ours.
Mr Gregson's written his name
in the fly-leaf. I see.
I nearly gave it to Her Ladyship,
but it seemed more suitable -
No. I'm the one who should have it.
Can you please put it on the table
beside my bed?
Of course.
Thank you.
Good afternoon.
Good afternoon. Thank you, Molesley.
It's good of you to come with us.
I must have something to do.
Where's your mother?
In the library.
I'm not sure Tom's visiting the
school is such a good idea.
He made a friend there of one of the
schoolmistresses when we were in London.
What's wrong with that?
I don't intend to explain, but I was
rather disappointed in him.
I would have hoped for better.
You're being very mysterious.
Can't I know the details?
You really don't need to.
There you are. How were they?
As dull as ever. They sent love.
What was the meeting like?
Have you accepted?
It wasn't me they came to see.
Well, they want me to give them some
land for the thing,
but they asked Carson to be the
Chairman.
Carson? Well, how nice.
I'm going upstairs to take off
my hat.
Well, she's pleased, anyway.
Congratulations.
I'm sure you will want me to thank
Lady Rose for consenting to present
the prizes today.
We're always glad of interest from
the Abbey.
And finally, thank you all for
coming.
It is most appreciated.
I'm glad Peter won a prize for
Geography. Well done, him.
He didn't get that from his father.
Is Mrs Drewe with you? No, she's at
home, looking after the young 'uns.
We ought to talk, but not here.
Tomorrow. At 11. By the stone barn.
You've been away.
I've been on a course.
I nearly wrote to tell you, but
I thought it might be presumptuous.
Well, I'm pleased to see you back.
That's a relief.
I thought I must have earned a black mark, making
you take me up to the house that night.
Hello, Miss Bunting.
Lady Rose. Well done.
Oh, it's not exactly difficult - giving out prizes.
I think we get thanked too much.
But that's the custom, isn't it?
We ought to head off, if we're to be
back before the gong.
The Rule of the Gong. It sounds like
life in a religious order!
Goodbye.
I'll see you again.
I hope so.
Spratt...
Offer Dr Clarkson some cake.
Then you may go.
Thank you.
I'm afraid serving me is a bit
beneath his dignity.
Even Spratt cannot always
live for pleasure.
how well do you know
Lord Merton?
Erm... I don't, really.
Oh.
Because I thought you might be
amused by how friendly he and Mrs
Crawley have become.
What Mrs Crawley chooses to do with
her private life is her own affair.
Oh, dear. I've annoyed you.
No, no, no, I'm not annoyed...
..although I am surprised to learn
that she entertains notions
of passing her time at drawing-room
receptions
and taking carriage rides in the
park.
Well, no-one takes carriage rides in
the park any more.
That's quite gone.
I wouldn't know.
You ought to meet Lord Merton
properly.
Come to luncheon on Saturday.
Mrs Crawley will be here
and so will he.
Well, that's quite an honour,
Lady Grantham. Are you sure?
Oh, it'll be fun. I'm hoping to
persuade dear Lady Shackleton
to be one of our number.
Mama's gone to bed. She wanted an
early night. I might go up too.
Come and sit here for a minute.
It doesn't really bother you they
want Carson, does it?
They'd be lucky to get him.
Even so, it makes you think.
Would a village delegation have
arrived in my grandfather's day
to ask his butler to head an appeal?
We're not living in your
grandfather's day. No, we are not.
So, they don't want me at the school
and they don't want me for the memorial.
Well, I want you.
I think you, Tom and I make a pretty
good team.
By the way, I've been looking into
crop rotation and grain sales -
And not every father hears that from
his daughter.
Mr Barrow...
I'm tired of waiting, Miss Baxter.
I'm tired of being bullied.
I got you this job and you knew what
I wanted in return.
So don't complain about it now.
Thank you, Madge. Good night.
Did you know Dicky Merton was in hot
pursuit of Isobel?
Mama says she's desperate to throw
him off.
I wonder.
What do you mean?
I don't believe your mother would enjoy the
transformation of Isobel into Lady Merton,
complete with a living husband, a proper
house and a solid position in the county.
That would not suit Mama at all.
Oh, don't be ridiculous. She'd be
thrilled, if that was what Isobel wanted.
Daisy, whatever are you doing up at this
hour? I thought you'd gone to bed long ago.
I just wanted to look at these.
What is it?
You can tell me.
Arithmetic Part 1?
Cost Accounting? What is this?
I was rubbish at numbers at school.
Well, all the best people were
rubbish at numbers at school.
But I don't know anything.
You talk about my working at
Mr Mason's farm, but how?
I couldn't balance the books if my
life depended on it.
Why do you need to? Because I want
to be grown up, Mrs Patmore.
I want responsibility.
I want to be an adult.
I can't just stand here, following
orders, for the rest of my life.
Well, I do see that.
The trouble is, I'm too stupid to
make out one solitary word.
You're not stupid, Daisy.
Far from it.
Then why can't I understand what's
written? Why can't I follow it?
Because...
Because I'm a pig-ignorant idiot.
Good night, Mrs Patmore.
Is this your secret lair?
It's not very secret,
but this is where I work.
And where you can hide away from the
rest of us?
Why do you never ask that
Miss Bunting up to the house?
Maybe I will. One day.
You live there too, you know.
I'm not sure where I live.
I feel sometimes I'm hanging in
mid-air.
Well, you mustn't think we don't
want you to have your own life.
I don't think that of Mary or Edith
or you.
But it would be hard for Lord and
Lady Grantham.
They'd have to get used to it.
Easier said than done.
I'd better get on.
So, I have your permission to
accept?
You don't need it.
It has nothing to do with your work.
No, but I wouldn't want to think it
was disagreeable for you.
We'd be delighted, Carson.
You'll be able to steer it through
the perils of village politics.
But traditionally, I feel it should
have been you, m'lord.
Maybe this will be a new tradition.
I know you hate not to be wanted,
but you're on so many committees.
What do you mean,
I hate not being wanted?
You think I'm taking too much
of an interest in Marigold.
It's Margie.
She thinks I'm there too often.
Because you've got a crush on me.
Well, that's better than the real
reason...
The real reason is a good reason to
love a child, m'lady.
Mothers should love their children.
How long have you known?
Since you asked me to take her in.
But you're quite safe.
It's not my place to judge you, and I
wouldn't, anyway.
But I should control my feelings?
I could say yes, but I don't believe
it's realistic.
I don't believe you could.
Then what are you saying?
We need a way for you to live the
truth, without telling the truth.
The die is cast. I've accepted.
His Lordship told me to take it.
There you are, then.
But he was sad.
Not with me, but maybe because
things are changing.
Well, they are,
whether we're sad about it or not.
I hope you're right about
Lord Gillingham.
What would I have felt if I'd
inherited a family with you?
You'd have loved them, I hope.
I would,
but I can't deny I'd prefer one of my
own. You'd feel the same.
Well, they do say a mother's love is
the strongest love there is.
But that's all in God's hands.
There's nothing we can do.
I can think of one thing. Mr Bates,
that sort of talk is beneath you.
I stand corrected.
I'll have it out of you. Fancy a
breath of air before the gong?
Thank you, Mr Molesley.
What's the matter with you? You've
not said a word all afternoon.
I went to the village and telephoned
her, to reason with her,
and I think it were a mistake.
It was never going to put her off.
Exactly.
The trouble is, she hates getting
older,
and I think that's at the bottom of
it.
Still, it's pathetic for a lady to
be pining over a footman.
Excuse me!
I think it shows very good taste.
My dear Lady Shackleton, how kind.
And you're on your way somewhere?
I am and I can't stay.
I'm dining with Philip,
and his wife sulks all night if
you're a minute late.
You should write a book:
Daughters-In-Law And How To Survive Them.
I like yours.
Yes, Cora does very well,
even if one cannot always rely on
her instincts.
I'd exchange her for mine in a trice.
Tell me: how well do you know
Lord Merton?
Oh, you know. We've seen each other
at parties for 40 years.
I worry that he's finding things
difficult since his wife died.
You're a widow.
You know what he's going through.
I suppose so, but I never saw them
as very devoted.
I should have thought he was glad to
be rid of her. I would be.
Then his sons are quite difficult.
I know what that's like.
Could you come to luncheon on
Saturday? Help me cheer him up?
Well, I'd love to.
Oh!
Of course, a single peer with a good
estate won't be lonely long,
if he doesn't want to be.
You sound like Mrs Bennett!
But what's he on about? He thinks
I know something about Mr Bates.
And do you?
Maybe.
Mr Bates may have done something he
wouldn't want known.
Do you mean a crime or...?
I'm not sure. I know he took a
journey, which I think he'd deny.
Look, I don't want to know any
more...
..but a pound to a penny,
Mr Barrow thinks he can use it
against Mr Bates.
Report him to Her Ladyship.
She'd soon put a stop to it.
I can't.
It's complicated, but I can't.
What is it?
What's what? You're doing something
funny with your head.
Sort of... tilting it.
I'm not, am I?
How do you think I look?
Why? Have you got a rash?
No, I've not got a rash.
That's all right, then.
No, what I meant was...
How old would you say I am?
I don't know. Maybe... 52?
Oh.
Why? How old are you?
51.
I've just had the strangest
telephone call.
Oh?
Do you remember Lady Anstruther?
You mean Jock Anstruther's widow?
That's it.
Her sister's Lady Renton and
her brother's Harry Mountevans.
I do remember her. Good-looking and
half Jock's age, and rather silly.
Well, silly or not, she's just rung
up and asked herself for tea. Oh.
Do people think we're a public house
on the Great North Road?
It certainly seems like it.
She's driving through the village on
Saturday and would love to see us.
What did you say?
Well, it's only tea.
Are we doing anything for your
anniversary?
What had you in mind?
Well, now that Tony's staying,
I thought we could invite some
people, make an evening of it.
Well, you girls ask some friends.
I'd like a young party for once,
instead of all those old duffers.
Hello.
Oh, Mary, I've got an idea.
I think it's sharp of Daisy to want
to learn to manage figures.
I'm afraid I agree with Mrs Patmore.
Why does she need to? She's a cook.
Cooks have to balance their budget.
She can learn enough for that
without being an expert in algebra.
She may not always be a cook.
Possibly not, but she won't be
Archimedes, either.
Sorry, but I don't think we should
encourage it.
I'm going up. I want to read a bit
before I turn out the light.
Oh, well done with your studies,
Daisy.
It's good to have more than one
string to your bow.
It's even better if you don't have
the brain of a kipper. Good night.
See? What did I tell you? She's lost
her confidence because of it.
And no mathematical skill
is worth that.
Why must Lady Anstruther choose
Saturday, of all days?
Ought we to invite her to
the dinner?
Isn't she staying somewhere else?
Tell me tomorrow who's coming, of
your pals. Keep the numbers even.
Well, Rose wants to invite a friend
of Tom's. He must feel so outnumbered.
Not that brother, I hope.
Someone local. Rose has met her.
So have I. She's quite respectable.
I think it would be nice.
Looking forward to seeing
Lord Gillingham?
I only saw him in London last week,
so I can remember what he looks like.
But I expect it's difficult to get
time alone in London.
Less difficult than when
I was a girl.
But yes, it'll be good to see him
here.
I haven't made up my mind, if that's
what you're thinking.
I wasn't thinking anything, but I
suppose you'll have to some time.
The older I get, the more I feel we
do these things very oddly.
Even now we must decide whether to
share our lives with someone
without ever spending any real time
with them.
Let alone... you know.
Of course, these days, some women do.
I was talking to Lady Cunard's
daughter last week,
and she was so graphic,
I almost fainted.
But then, what could be more
important?
To make sure that that side of things
is right...
..before we tie ourselves to someone
for ever?
I'm afraid I'm too old-fashioned
for you, m'lady.
I need hardly say you're not to
repeat a word to Bates.
Of course not, m'lady.
What do you make of this?
Blimey. What does that mean?
As you know, Lord Gillingham arrives today,
but there's been no mention of a valet.
There was enough mention of the last
one. Poor Mr Green. A terrible end.
Let's not rake over that now.
As I say, His Lordship may have a valet,
but these days we can't be sure, so...
Yes, Mr Carson?
Not you. Mr Bates, would you keep
an eye on him, if necessary?
Certainly, Mr Carson.
Mr Molesley, have you...?
Have I what, Mr Carson?
Er... never mind.
Arms down. Relax.
I'm sorry. They've only just told me
you were waiting.
Oh, I've not been here long.
I wanted to see you after I read
your letter.
It wasn't meant to be confusing.
No. But why won't you come?
Because I don't want to be part of
some sort of a... prank.
What prank?
I may not have been presented at
Court, Lady Rose,
but I do know it's usual to be
invited to dinner by the hostess.
And shouldn't Mr Branson have played
a part in it?
Lady Grantham asked us to invite some
younger guests to liven up the evening,
so Mary and I thought it would be nice
for Tom to have a friend there. That's all.
I'm right, then? He doesn't know.
No, it would be a surprise for him,
but a nice surprise.
And Lady Grantham is aware of this?
Completely. She wants you to come.
I could have managed Lord Gillingham.
No need to burden Mr Bates with him.
I think Mr Carson forgets that
I'm a valet, too.
I know, and it seems a bit ironic
for Mr Bates to dress him.
Why is it ironic?
I don't know why I said that.
Why did you say it, Miss Baxter?
Er... it was rubbish. Nonsense.
Now, if you'll excuse me, I'm late.
Oh, how nice. I wanted to call on
you, but I didn't like to be a bother.
I've been quite busy lately, helping
with the out-patient clinic.
Dr Clarkson.
Oh. Lady Grantham.
May I present Dr Clarkson?
I think you know Lord Merton.
I think we have met, yes.
We were talking about your clinic.
Oh, you mustn't bore him.
As a matter of fact, I'd be
interested to - The Lady Shackleton.
Oh, my dear, how prompt you are.
Your daughter-in-law has trained you
well.
Now, you remember Lord Merton?
Of course. How are you?
And how's that lovely garden of
yours?
Oh, still lovely. Largely because
I have the same lovely gardener.
I don't think we've met since dear
Lady Merton's funeral.
I do hope things are sorting
themselves out.
You've gone to a lot of trouble.
Mmm. I like to help where I can.
Oh, Spratt. Shall we go in?
Lord Gillingham.
Ah, here he is.
Tony, welcome.
Lovely to see you all.
I'm afraid you've missed luncheon.
I ate on the train.
A cup of coffee, then?
That would be perfect.
Carson, I must congratulate you.
They're building a memorial in the
village, and Carson is the Chairman.
I like the idea of these things.
To give people a solid focus for
their grief and gratitude.
I agree, My Lord. I hope
His Lordship's happy about it.
My being Chairman, I mean.
He is. Or, at any rate, he will be.
So, how are the famous pigs doing?
Pretty well.
They're earning their keep and more.
I'm going out this afternoon, to get
some rabbits for Mrs Patmore. Come with me.
I'll find you a gun and you can see
what we've been up to.
I'll come too, although I warn you -
I'm not very good at picking up.
Well, if I'm shooting,
you won't have to.
That I do not believe.
Could you spare me for an hour?
I think everything's under control.
I just want to run down to the post
office. I won't be long.
So, will you be travelling north in
August for the grouse?
You talk as if my sole concern is
the sporting year, Dr Clarkson.
The truth is, these days, I hold a
book more often than a 12-bore.
You must miss it.
Not particularly. Thank you. Er...
As a matter of fact, he's more
interested in medicine than sport.
I find that hard to believe.
You sound a little prejudiced.
Not at all.
He seems a nice enough example of
the type, I grant you.
Er...
But, as you say yourself, we're not
members of that tribe, you and I.
Spratt...
I think Dr Clarkson would like
some coffee.
And don't be such a snob.
I'm determined to get you over to
Sheriff Hutton.
The children are in the main house
now. I've been banished to a cottage.
Did you move before Hubert died?
No.
To be honest, I didn't want to go at
all, but I've got used to it.
Apart from anything else, I've never
been warm before!
Morning.
So, why did you talk about Mr Bates
and Lord Gillingham's valet?
What's the connection? Tell me.
There's no point trying to find
Mr Molesley...
..because he can't help you now.
If that's how you want to play it,
I'll give you until upstairs dinner
has finished,
after which I will ask to speak to Her Ladyship
and I will tell her your story.
Do you hear what I'm saying?
I can't tell you what I don't know.
But you know something.
And I think it links Mr Bates to the
dead valet.
I'm impressed by what I've seen.
Tom's a good partner,
so I'm lucky.
I'm the lucky one.
Tom, what about your American plans?
Oh, I don't know. Nothing's fixed.
But never fear. Mary is more than
ready to manage without me.
That's your man.
So, you're not frightened of being
left on your own to control your Papa?
I understand him better now,
and I think he'd say the same of me.
So he's not fighting all change,
then?
No, but he likes proper research.
You see, I want to improve
how we sell our grain.
If I make a good case for it,
he'll agree.
How positive you are.
I've decided to live in the present
and not spend my life
regretting the past or dreading the
future.
I shall try to follow your example.
Do you dread the future?
Only if I have to live it
without you.
Tony, I do love you, you know.
In my cold and unfeeling way.
Then why not say yes?
I don't want to get it wrong.
I'd like to marry again.
I've come that far.
But I intend to be as happy with my
second husband as I was with my first.
It's bound to be a risk on some
level.
You have to take a chance.
The stable clock's fast.
We ought to get back.
By the way, Bates will look after you,
if you haven't brought a man of your own.
Oh, that's rather a luxury for me
these days. I have no valet now.
Our butler takes care of me at home,
but when I travel I usually fend for myself.
Do you mind?
It makes things simpler.
I'd love to make our lives simpler.
Hm.
It's a nightmare when guests are a
nuisance and I feel so guilty,
but I wasn't sure we were even going
to make it down the drive.
But what happened, exactly?
Well, there was this terrible noise.
A sort of rattle, rattle, bang,
bang.
And then the engine just seemed to
lose its power.
We'll get Tom to take a look at it.
Oh, how kind.
But I think my chauffeur, Weaver,
seems to have it in hand.
Could I just use your telephone
and tell my hosts I won't be able to
get to them tonight?
But what will you do? Oh, we passed
a public house in the village,
and I asked Weaver to see if they
had any rooms.
You can't possibly stay at the pub.
Why not? I'm tougher than I look.
You must stay here. We have people
coming to dinner, so it'll be easy.
Oh, yes, it's perfect.
Oh, that's sweet.
Molesley,
you look very Latin all of a sudden.
Do you have Italian blood?
No, m'lord. Not that I'm aware.
Or Spanish? Or Irish?
James... please tell Mrs Hughes that
Lady Anstruther will be staying.
If she could prepare
Princess Amelia.
Very good, Your Ladyship.
Go now. Tell her everything.
You don't know what you're asking.
I may not know your story, but I do know
it'll be worse if Mr Barrow tells her first.
Yes. You're right.
Thank you.
Why is she here?
They don't know her, do they?
Well, if they do, she never told me.
What are you going to say to her?
Who says I'll get the chance to say
anything? Go on. Have it out.
She's playing with you
like a cat with a vole.
James... did you know about
Lady Anstruther's visit?
No, Mr Carson. Why should I?
Didn't you work for her one time?
I'm sure I've got a reference
from her somewhere.
But that was quite a while back,
wasn't it?
Well, she's made extra work for
everyone.
That's all I know.
What do you mean, you need to tell
me something before Barrow does?
Mr Barrow wants to tell you about
something in my past, m'lady.
I've a secret, you see.
A bad secret.
I don't understand. What secret?
How does he know it?
I was a friend of his sister's
when we were young.
But if he knew something wrong about you,
why would he put you forward for the job?
I think you had better tell me.
Very well.
A few years ago, I worked in London,
as a lady's maid
for a Mrs Benton who... lived with her
husband in Ovington Square.
Go on.
I was there for about six months,
and then I...
And then you what?
I...
..took some jewellery belonging to
the mistress.
A necklace, a couple of bracelets,
some rings.
You took them?
I tried to make it look like a
burglary, but it didn't work.
And Mrs Benton reported the theft?
They took me up a few hours later.
My fingerprints were everywhere.
And to make it worse...
..I never gave the stolen things
back.
Why not?
Because, by then, I didn't have them.
What happened?
I went to prison. For three years.
Thank you, Baxter.
Very good, m'lady.
What do you make of our
mysterious visitor?
Tom said he went to look at the car
and could find nothing wrong.
Maybe the chauffeur mended it.
Maybe.
We ought to go down.
Will there be anything else?
I don't think so. Thank you.
It's been quite a treat.
You don't travel with a valet
these days, m'lord?
No, no. When Green died,
I never replaced him.
We were all shocked by the death of
Mr Green so soon after he was here.
Yes. Of course.
Had he been with you long?
Not very long, no.
Right. Thank you.
Well...?
I told her.
Now, I'm not asking what you said, but I
want to be sure that you held nothing back.
Good.
How was she?
I don't know.
Shocked, but not unkind.
Then His Lordship walked in,
so that was that.
The point is, if she allows you to
stay,
you're here in a truthful way and
not in a lie.
And if I'm not allowed to stay?
Well, you're still not caught
in a lie.
That's what matters.
I will tell you the story one day.
But I'm loath to... forfeit your
good opinion, and I know I would.
No, you won't.
You don't trust me yet,
but I'm on your side.
Mr Molesley, I need that up in the
servery. Now.
Yes, Mr Carson.
Jimmy... I ought to scold you.
Why did you ignore my letters?
You're a very naughty boy.
Show Her Ladyship where to find the
drawing room, James.
Of course.
Will you come this way, m'lady?
I feel so guilty, pushing into
a family celebration.
You'd be an ornament at any
gathering. Oh, how nice. Thank you.
No cocktails?
I thought everyone had them now.
Not at Downton. Our butler tried
them once and he hasn't recovered.
Oh, look at your parents.
34 years. I'd never manage it.
That's the advantage of an older
husband. One gets an early release!
Miss Sarah Bunting.
What on earth is she doing here?
I asked her. Cora said I could.
Have I done something wrong?
She's the teacher I told you about.
After her behaviour while we were in London,
I don't think she's a suitable guest.
Let me introduce you.
Kitty Colthurst. Sarah Bunting.
Miss Bunting's a teacher.
Oh, golly! How clever.
What do you teach?
The usual things. Writing.
Mathematics.
Crikey. Writing's almost beyond me,
and I wouldn't know where to start
with mathematics!
Well, then, you must marry someone
rich enough to ensure you never need to.
Oh...
What are you doing here?
Lady Rose invited me.
Rose, did you ask Lord Grantham?
Wasn't Cora's permission enough?
How are you?
I'm exhausted.
Two parties in one day
is too much for me.
Was your luncheon a success?
You must ask Cousin Isobel.
We've cast the net wide tonight.
Can't Tom have a friend of his own?
Oh, of course.
But it's time he decided whether he
is fish, flesh, fowl or good red herring.
Well, I think it's nice to see
an intelligent face here.
Miss Bunting has been shocking us
with her support for the Prime Minister.
But surely, most of the country must support
him, or he wouldn't be Prime Minister.
There is an unanswerable logic in
that. Oh, quite.
There's an alliance that does not
bode well.
I quite agree with you.
Aren't you being very snobbish?
We're being realistic - something
your generation has such trouble with.
Her chauffeur says there's nothing
wrong with the car that he could
find, so there's a mystery.
See? She's here to see you.
I don't know what she wants.
Don't you? Because I do.
It's embarrassing.
I have a feeling it could get a lot
more embarrassing
if you don't find a way to keep her
quiet.
Take that.
Marriage is a lottery, as we are
often told,
but I am a man who has drawn
a winning ticket.
I have been awarded a bumper prize:
beauty, brains, a heart,
a conscience, all in one.
I give you my Cora, the best
companion in the world.
Mama.
Lady Grantham.
What a tribute.
Indeed. If only it were true!
What's happened to Molesley's hair?
Carson, Lady Mary tells me that
you're to lead the Memorial Committee.
That is so, madam. Yes.
You'll drive it splendidly.
Rose, is that friend of yours
terribly clever?
She's Tom's friend, not mine,
but I think so. Yes.
She certainly thought I was
terribly stupid.
Well, let's not shoot her down
for that.
No, thank you.
Do you know that footman?
Yes, he used to work for me.
It's always nice to see
a friendly face.
Especially a friendly, pretty face.
I'm not convinced these memorials
are a good idea,
but I suppose that's a different
issue.
Why not? Won't they give people
a focus for their sorrow?
And a reminder of the sacrifices
that were made.
If it were a memorial service,
then I might agree,
but a stone edifice on the green,
to remind us for ever of death and a
pointless war - what's the good of that?
To say nothing of the waste of
money.
Forgive me, but you're talking
nonsense.
Forgive me, but I suppose
she's allowed an opinion.
Not that opinion. Not in this house.
I think what she means is -
She is here as your friend,
so of course you must defend her.
But was the war worth fighting?
What did it achieve, beyond the
Russian Revolution?
Millions of men dead and no more
'justice' than there was before.
You are wrong, both of you.
But we must strive to keep things
light.
It's a pity they didn't want you
on their Committee.
You put up a stout defence of
their intentions.
They do want His Lordship on the
Committee.
Forgive me, My Lord.
I'd have told you later, but they
held a meeting this afternoon,
and they would like you
as their patron.
Oh, how nice. I dare say that was
always their plan.
I dare say it was, Your Ladyship.
I should be glad to accept.
Now, if you can all put
your swords away,
perhaps we can finish our dinner
in a civilised manner.
But I admire it, when young people
stand up for their principles.
Principles are like prayers.
Noble, of course,
but awkward at a party.
James, did my eyes deceive me,
or did Lady Anstruther pass you
a note during dinner?
Yes, Mr Carson.
Can I see it?
He's thrown it away.
She just wanted to remind him that
he once worked for her, Mr Carson.
Even so, it's most irregular.
But it wasn't his fault, was it? He
could hardly slap her hand away.
Get that up to the drawing room.
I gather from Mr Molesley that you
gave the good news to His Lordship.
Ah, that is correct.
How did you get them to agree?
I said I wouldn't serve if they
didn't make him Patron.
And have you told him that?
He doesn't need to know everything,
Mrs Hughes.
Nobody has to know everything.
I've enjoyed myself.
Both gatherings were interesting,
in their different ways.
You get on well with Lord Merton.
I know that.
I do, but Cousin Violet had other
plans for him at luncheon.
Where is Granny?
She said goodbye to your mother, but
she wanted to slip away.
The day of parties had taken
its toll.
Before I go, I want to meet the
staff downstairs.
You don't think you've made enough
of a statement?
What about you?
I know. I got a bit carried away.
I thought you were splendid.
Cheer up.
You're putting quite a dampener on
the evening.
Really? I thought only imbeciles
were happy all the time.
Here she comes.
The Boudicca of the North Riding.
Thank you so much for having me.
It was a pleasure.
Wasn't it, Robert?
I want to thank your cook before I
go, and the other servants.
I'm afraid they'll be sitting down to
supper, and we don't like to disturb them.
I won't be more than a minute.
Of course you must go down.
They'd be delighted.
I assume you heard the way she spoke
to me at dinner.
Of course, but how does it help to
answer rudeness with rudeness?
Is everything satisfactory, m'lord?
No, it is not.
And can you please keep Molesley in the
kitchens until his hair stops turning blue?
What are you doing?
Setting out the breakfast trays for
Her Ladyship and Lady Mary.
Not Lady Rose and Lady Edith?
Unmarried young ladies eat breakfast
in the dining room. Oh, do they?
Thank you again, and I'm glad to
meet you.
I felt I had to put faces to
his stories.
What stories are those?
Oh, that's a dangerous question.
We may not like the answer!
Do you work in the school? I teach mathematics,
handwriting and spelling, mainly.
You must be so clever.
I wouldn't say that.
Come and meet the others.
Goodbye.
That's such a different path.
It is,
but it doesn't mean it's better than
the one you've chosen.
Your Ladyship, might I have a word?
I'm very sorry to say it,
but I've learned something that
makes me feel both responsible and guilty.
Would this have to do with Baxter?
Because, if it concerns her criminal
record, then I know all about it.
Do you, m'lady?
What I don't understand is why you
placed a convicted felon
in my household, in my bedroom,
when you knew every detail
of her past.
I wanted her to have another chance.
Don't you think that should have
been my decision, in my own house?
Yes, m'lady. Perhaps it should.
So... why tell me now? Because, if you have
been using your knowledge against her,
I'll have to consider your future
here.
Indeed, whether you have one at all.
I just thought I'd been wrong and
you ought to know.
I see. Well, now I do.
Good night.
You think you're so clever,
don't you?
Has Miss Bunting gone?
Yes. She got a lift down to the
village with Mrs Crawley.
That was nice of her.
I wanted to apologise, for arguing
with you at dinner.
You were nothing, compared to her.
She has her views - that's true.
But I must confess, they remind me
of how I used to feel.
Is that what you want, Tom?
To go back, when you've come so far?
I've come a long way from who I was.
That's true.
And is it a bad thing?
- We're not lovers, you know.
- What?
That time when you were in London,
you thought that we'd got up to
something. We never did.
As Sybil's father, this is not an
easy conversation for me,
but if I was wrong, then I am sorry.
The truth is, I worry less about that
than if Miss Bunting is taking you
back into the role of rebel and hater.
I'm not a hater.
I don't hate anyone.
Least of all you.
Well, that is a more cheerful note to
say 'good night' on.
Isis!
But why didn't you give the jewels
back?
You say you didn't have them by
then, but who did?
More than that,
why did you do it at all?
You don't strike me as being greedy.
You were working. You were earning.
Did you dislike Mrs Benton?
Was she harsh?
No, m'lady. She was a kind woman.
That only makes it more mysterious.
I won't start concocting excuses for
myself. There are no excuses.
There may not be excuses, but there
is missing information.
You've shocked me, Baxter.
Profoundly. I can't deny it.
You have every reason, m'lady. So, am
I to take it that I am dismissed?
Your work is excellent, and I have
never sacked a servant
that gave me no cause for complaint.
Have I your word you will not commit
this crime again?
I will never commit any crime again.
Not as long as I live.
You may stay until I make
a decision.
I cannot tell you how long
that will be,
and I do not at all promise
I'll keep you on.
No.
Very well.
I think we should leave it there
for now.
I hope we don't have to see too much
more of Miss Bunting.
Lady Rose told Madge she liked her.
And she seemed nice when she came
downstairs.
Maybe, but she makes Papa say things
he doesn't mean,
and I know he hates himself for it
afterwards.
Mr Molesley...
I do not know why you have treated
your hair with a special substance -
Well, I -
But I can only say
that the effect on your appearance
is not what you would have it.
Take steps, Mr Molesley. Take steps.
You will remain below stairs
until you do.
Well... So, Lady Mary's not quite so
ladylike, after all.
Me next.
You think I'm mad, don't you?
It doesn't matter what I think.
Maybe she just wants to talk.
Maybe I'm the missing Tsarevich!
The trouble is, I can't resist it.
Not when it's offered on a plate.
Well, you're not alone there.
Now, if you can stay with her
until three,
you'll get back to your room
without being noticed.
I'll watch until you're in there. If you hear
me speak, just keep walking past her door.
Thanks, Mr Barrow.
Thomas. I mean it.
You're a real pal.
Well, I try to be.
But, Tony... you really shouldn't be
in here.
Of course I shouldn't.
Why are you, then?
Because you're in love with me.
Am I?
Well, you said so yourself. You were
torn between me and Charles Blake,
but I think you've decided
and I'm the winner.
Well, thank goodness that's settled.
The trouble is, you want to be sure.
Well, surer than the customs
of well-bred courtship will allow.
Go on.
I want you to come away.
Just for a week, maybe less.
But on our own, and we'll spend
the days... talking.
And the nights?
We'll spend those together, too.
I want us to be lovers, Mary.
I want us to know everything there
is to know about each other.
And then after that, I believe you
will be sure.
If Papa was here,
he'd hit you on the nose.
I'm trying to convince you
to marry me.
That's not the normal purpose of
seducers.
I don't think he'd see it that way.
What do you say to my scandalous
suggestion?
No-one must ever find out.
Fire!
What?
Oh, my God. George!
I've got Sybbie and George.
Thank God! Mary, you take them.
Tony, go with her. Tom, come with me.
You know where the sand buckets
are kept.
Good god! Barrow, is she all right?
I think so, m'lord.
We must get her outside.
Quickly, Tom!
Tom, get the hose!
Rose, wake Mrs Hughes and the maids.
She'll do the rest.
We must alert the firemen. Who knows
where to find Drewe's number?
I do.
And save the dog!
Barrow, hurry up! Get her away from
the smoke. I'll check the bedrooms.
Let me check the rooms, m'lord.
Now, man!
Fire!
There's a fire.
Well, I'll see you both downstairs.
Everybody outside. There's a fire.
James? James? Where's James?
Peter, look in the bathroom
for James.
Mr Molesley, hurry along, please.
Here, Tom!
Mrs Patmore, do be careful.
Don't worry. Don't worry.
We'll take over now, m'lord.
Thank you.
How are you feeling?
All right, I think.
But I've been terribly stupid.
Don't worry about that now.
Lord Grantham, I may sneak away
before breakfast.
Would you forgive me?
I have quite a way to go.
Perhaps that would be a good idea.
M'lord...
Barrow, we have to thank you -
for raising the alarm and rescuing
Lady Edith so bravely.
What were you doing on the gallery?
Oh, just keeping an eye on things.
Well, thank goodness you were!
I was angry with you before and
I was tempted to take it further,
but I accept that you have earned
our goodwill by your actions tonight.
Thank you, m'lady.
What's going on? What's happening?
Don't worry. It's almost over.
Mr Bates wanted to come, to see you
were safe. We were so worried.
We're fine. Lady Edith chose to set
fire to her room, but we're fine.
I'll see if there's anything
I can do.
He's calmed down now, but he was in
a real state.
He does get so worked up about
things.
I can imagine.
I don't wish to be harsh,
but I have a feeling
James would be better
employed elsewhere.
Oh?
Please don't ask me why I think so,
but I suspect his ambitions rather outstrip
what a career as a footman will yield.
As Your Lordship wishes.
Give him a good reference.
We don't want it talked about.
Understood, m'lord.
All clear now, m'lord. No real
damage beyond Lady Edith's bedroom.
Well, that's something.
We can all go back inside!
The excitement is over.
Might Lady Edith sleep in His
Lordship's dressing room tonight, m'lady?
Since the bed's made up.
Of course.
I'm just going to thank the firemen,
Papa. Right.
Have you had any ideas?
Yes, and it's a simple one.
You are going to take a great
interest in little Marigold, m'lady.
Of course. We just need to introduce
the notion carefully,
so everyone accepts and believes it.
You're to sleep in His Lordship's
dressing room tonight,
and we'll see what can be saved
tomorrow.
Thank you, Mrs Hughes.
You have heard the voice of
His Majesty King George V.
I'm sorry if I've hurt you.
And the mist is clearing around the
lithe figure of Tony Gillingham?
You do know she's a thief?
There must be more to it.
Mrs Crawley has been distracted
lately,
with Lord Merton frisking around
her skirts.
I didn't kill him personally.
I didn't shoot the Imperial Family.
Is this what they call a lively
exchange of views?
Subtitles by MemoryOnSmells
http://UKsubtitles.ru.